Yearbook; Collection ua807
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Yearbook Collection
1900-2014
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua807
6.93 cubic ft.
This collection is made up of the published yearbooks of the New York State Normal College, the New York State College for Teachers, and the State University of New York at Albany.
Historical Note
The earliest copy of the yearbook in our possession is from 1900, and was titled the "Neon." It went through several name changes including "The Senior Book" and "Our Book" until the name "Pedagogue" was chosen in 1913. The "Pedagogue" unlike the other renditions of the yearbook, included more than just simple photographs and names of faculty and students, like some earlier editions had. Each club was represented with a photograph and a list of their members, as well as advertisements for institutions that had contributed to the published of the book. This format has not varied.
The yearbook remained under the name "Pedagogue" until 1963 when it was renamed the "Torch." This name change coincided with he beginning of the construction of the new uptown campus. It was an important part of the first edition of the "Torch" since the campus population had been growing rapidly, and this was remarked on in the yearbook itself. In the 1970s' there were multiple editions of the "Torch" which were used as stumps in which the students made political statements or protests. The 1972 copy had photographs of a Vietnamese child's head printed multiple times on each page, intermingled with the photographs of the students. Copies such as this would focus heavily on the level of campus unrest at the University at Albany, as well as across the country. The "Torch" continues to be the published year book for SUNY Albany
Scope and Contents
This collection is made up of the yearbooks for the New York State Normal College, the New York State College for Teachers, and the State University of New York at Albany, and encompasses the years 1900-2014. For the first ten years there are only copies for the years 1900 and 1904, though proceeding after that every published copy up to 2014 is in our collection.
Arrangement of the Collection
Collection is arranged chronologically based on the publication year of the book.
Acquisition Information
All items in this collection were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Related Materials
Related collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives can be found in the subject guide for Criminal Justice and Prisons.
Access
Anyone is welcome to visit our Reading Room during normal hours and view the yearbooks. The only exception is the 1974 Torch which is restricted due to the presence of personally identifiable information.
We can now also complete remote digitization requests for yearbooks in-house. Typically, most yearbooks take about 90-120 minutes to scan and process, but since yearbooks are often requested, we will charge a reduced rate of $60.00 to digitize a yearbook and make it available online. Please Make a Remote Request or contact us if you are interested in funding yearbook digitization.
Content warning
The department's yearbooks date back to 1900, and each of these student publications reflects the time in which it was published. Yearbooks may contain derogatory images and harmful language that do not reflect the current values of the University Libraries or the University at Albany, SUNY. These yearbooks also document challenging topics that respective editors elected to cover. This material may be distressing or of concern for researchers.
College yearbooks; College Students; UAlbany Student Groups; School yearbooks
- Neon, 1900; 105 vol. (Volume 1)
- Yearbook, 1904 (Volume 2)
- Our Book, 1911 (Volume 3)
- Senior Book, 1912 (Volume 4)
- Pedagogue, 1913 (Volume 5)
- Pedagogue, 1914 (Volume 6)
- Pedagogue, 1915 (Volume 7)
- Pedagogue, 1916 (Volume 8)
- Pedagogue, 1917 (Volume 9)
- Pedagogue, 1918 (Volume 10)
- Pedagogue, 1919 (Volume 11)
- Pedagogue, 1920 (Volume 12)
- Pedagogue, 1921 (Volume 13)
- Pedagogue, 1922 (Volume 14)
- Pedagogue, 1923 (Volume 15)
  Content warning
  This item contains derogatory and potentially harmful depictions of East Asian peoples. These representations reflect the prejudices and biases of the time in which they were created and may be offensive or distressing. We present this material as part of the historical record, not as an endorsement of the views it contains.
- Pedagogue, 1924 (Volume 16)
- Pedagogue, 1925 (Volume 17)
- Pedagogue, 1926 (Volume 18)
- Pedagogue, 1927 (Volume 19)
- Pedagogue, 1928 (Volume 20)
- Pedagogue, 1929 (Volume 21)
- Pedagogue, 1930 (Volume 22)
- Pedagogue, 1931 (Volume 23)
- Pedagogue, 1932 (Volume 24)
- Pedagogue, 1933 (Volume 25)
  This item contains derogatory and potentially harmful depictions of indigenous peoples. These representations reflect the prejudices and biases of the time in which they were created and may be offensive or distressing. We present this material as part of the historical record, not as an endorsement of the views it contains.
- Pedagogue, 1934 (Volume 26)
- Pedagogue, 1935 (Volume 27)
- Pedagogue, 1936 (Volume 28)
- Pedagogue, 1937 (Volume 29)
- Pedagogue, 1938 (Volume 30)
- Pedagogue, 1939 (Volume 31)
- Pedagogue, 1940 (Volume 32)
- Pedagogue, 1941 (Volume 33)
- Pedagogue, 1942 (Volume 34)
- Pedagogue, 1943 (Volume 35)
- Pedagogue, 1944 (Volume 36)
- Pedagogue, 1945 (Volume 37)
- Pedagogue, 1946 (Volume 38)
- Pedagogue, 1947 (Volume 39)
- Pedagogue, 1948 (Volume 40)
- Pedagogue, 1949 (Volume 41)
- Pedagogue, 1950 (Volume 42)
- Pedagogue, 1951 (Volume 43)
- Pedagogue, 1952 (Volume 44)
- Pedagogue, 1953 (Volume 45)
- Pedagogue, 1954 (Volume 46)
- Pedagogue, 1955 (Volume 47)
- Pedagogue, 1956 (Volume 48)
- Pedagogue, 1957 (Volume 49)
- Pedagogue, 1958 (Volume 50)
- Pedagogue, 1959 (Volume 51)
- Pedagogue, 1960 (Volume 52)
- Pedagogue, 1961 (Volume 53)
- Pedagogue, 1962 (Volume 54)
- Torch, 1963 (Volume 55)
- Torch, 1964 (Volume 56)
- Torch, 1965 (Volume 57)
- Torch, 1966 (Volume 58)
- Torch, 1967 (Volume 59)
  This item depicts activities that are insensitive and may be offensive. We present this material as part of the historical record, not as an endorsement of the behavior it contains.
- Torch, 1968 (Volume 60)
  Content Warning
  This item contains images that may be offensive or distressing.
- Torch, 1969 (Volume 61)
- Torch, 1970 (Volume 62)
- Torch, 1971 (Volume 63)
- Torch, 1972 (Volume 64)
  Biographical / Historical
  The 1972 Torch was edited by Ronald Simmons, a gay Black man whose deep involvement in LGBTQ+ activism began during his time as a student at UAlbany from 1968-1972. The Torch was independently produced but funded from the Student Association. When the book was released in April 1972 there was considerable opposition to the inclusion of provocatively graphic images of a deceased Vietnamese man among the senior portraits. The Student Association disavowed the book and froze the Torch budget. Student leaders called the book "a catastrophe" that offended people and exerted more control over the next editor who had to agree to certain guidelines before the yearbook budget was unfrozen.
  After earning two graduate degrees at UAlbany in the 1970s, Ronald Simmons completed his doctorate at Howard University in 1987 and became a pivotal figure in Washington D.C.'s gay and lesbian activist community as it confronted HIV and AIDS. He became involved in several Black LGBT activist efforts and groundbreaking organizations such as the National Coalition of Black Gays and the DC Coalition of Black Lesbian and Gay Men. Following his own HIV diagnosis in 1990, Dr. Simmons became Executive Director of Us Helping Us, a pioneering Black gay men's health organization from 1992 to 2016.
  Scope and Contents
  The 1972 Torch yearbook is a curated collection of photography and text capturing student life on campus, including discussions of sex and depictions of drug use. It documents or discusses protests to the state's response to the Attica uprising, environmentalism, poverty in Albany, feminism, gay and lesbian liberation.
  This item contains graphic images from the Vietnam War that may be unsettling or distressing to viewers. These images were intentionally provocative, intended as a political statement against the war.
- Torch, 1973 (Volume 65)
  This item contains depictions of blackface, nudity, drug use, and obscene gestures. Some of these representations reflect the prejudices and biases or the culture of the time in which they were created and may be offensive or distressing. We present this material as part of the historical record, not as an endorsement of the views or behavior it contains. The 1972 Torch yearbook was controversial when published. The addition of a January 10, 1973 Times-Union opinion column in the 1973 Torch about the 1972 yearbook calling it a "printed abortion" and claiming that it was met with "opposition from many of the students" suggests that some of images on the pages immediately following, involving nudity and drug use, may have been deliberately included as a response from the 1973 editors.
- Torch, 1974 (Volume 66)
  Conditions Governing Access
  The 1974 Torch is restricted due to the presence of personally identifiable information. Students identified themselves using personally identifiable information as a form of protest. Please consult an archivist for more details on viewing this item.
- Torch, 1975 (Volume 67)
- Torch Cover, 1976 (Volume 68)
- Torch Volume 1, 1976 (Volume 68)
- Torch Volume 2, 1976 (Volume 68)
- Torch, 1977 (Volume 69)
  - Robert Blumenthal, et. al vinyl phonographic record (33 1/3 RPM) included in 1977 Torch
- Torch, 1978 (Volume 70)
  This item contains potentially harmful portrayals of Asian people. These representations reflect the prejudices and biases of the time in which they were created and may be offensive or distressing. We present this material as part of the historical record, not as an endorsement of the views it contains.
- Torch, 1979 (Volume 71)
- Torch, 1980 (Volume 72)
- Torch, 1981 (Volume 73)
- Torch, 1982 (Volume 74)
- Torch, 1983 (Volume 75)
- Torch, 1984 (Volume 76)
- Torch, 1985 (Volume 77)
- Torch, 1986 (Volume 78)
- Torch, 1987 (Volume 79)
- Torch, 1988 (Volume 80)
- Torch, 1989 (Volume 81)
- Torch, 1990 (Volume 82)
- Torch, 1991 (Volume 83)
- Torch, 1992 (Volume 84)
- Torch, 1993 (Volume 85)
- Torch, 1994 (Volume 86)
- Torch, 1995 (Volume 87)
- Torch, 1996 (Volume 88)
- Torch, 1997 (Volume 89)
- Torch, 1998 (Volume 90)
- Torch, 1999 (Volume 91)
- Torch, 2000 (Volume 92)
- Torch, 2001 (Volume 93)
- Torch, 2002 (Volume 94)
- Torch, 2003 (Volume 95)
- Torch, 2004 (Volume 96)
- Torch, 2005 (Volume 97)
- Torch, 2006 (Volume 98)
- Torch, 2007 (Volume 99)
- Torch, 2008 (Volume 100)
- Torch, 2009 (Volume 101)
- Torch, 2010 (Volume 102)
- Torch, 2011 (Volume 103)
- Torch, 2012 (Volume 104)
- Torch, 2013 (Volume 105)
- Torch, 2014 (Volume 106)
- Torch, 2022 (Volume 107)